eventually this load does complete and
let's say it brings us a value of 700
and it's marked is done now we're going
to do the branch and the add meanwhile
we are going to be checking whether we
can commit this instruction and we can
because it's marked is done and it's the
next instruction to commit so we will
commit this instruction which will
result in moving the commit pointer here
and writing this value of 700 to
register r1 and also making the rat now
point here now let's suppose that the
branch takes longer to figure out than
the add
so this add completes produces a value
of let's say 3 and it's done and that's
all that happens here again this result
would have been written to the registers
thus permanently changing r2 and that's
all that happens now know that this
result of tree would not have been
written to the registers even with
tomasulo's algorithm because the
renaming for r2 is pointing not to this
instruction meaning that we would have
kept in the registers the value of 2
that we would have written for the
divide because that's the latest r2 but
in this case we don't do any of that we
just keep the values in the Rob as is
eventually we get to resolve this branch
and figure out that it's been
mispredicted so now the branch will be
marked as done we will now start
fetching from the correct instructions
but the question is how do we get rid of
the ones that we had wrong well what we
do is we annotate here that there's has
been a misprediction of this branch and
that's all that happens as a result of
its execution and we don't really fix
the misprediction we continue fetching
the wrong instructions because we don't
know how to get rid of these until the
commit reach is the point of the branch
so when we commit this branch we realize
that after this branch we were fetching
the wrong instructions the PC that the
branch should have created is different
from the PC we have actually used at
that point what we do is we commit the
branch normally it doesn't write to any
registers so the commit just moves this
but if it's been mispredicted and it was
what we do is we do the recovery before
we restart the fetch from the correct
place how do we do this recovery well
with the Rob based processor at the
point where the commit has reached the
branch the registers contain exactly the
values they need to contain at the point
of the branch all of the instructions
prior to the branch have been committed
which means that their updates have been
reflected in the registers and none of
the instructions after the branch have
updated the registers so the registers
contain exactly the correct value at the
point of the branch to undo these
instructions what we need to do is two
things one is reverse the issuing of
these instructions by simply making the
Rob empty at this point so after we have
committed the branch we make the Rob
ante by simply putting the issue point
in the same place so we will issue
instructions again into these slots we
of course as we issue them on mark this
done bit also the rat now contains the
wrong values but the question is what
are the right values for the rat well
because the registers contain exactly
the correct values as of this point
undoing the damage in the rat simply
consists of rewriting whatever is in the
rat so that each rat entry points
directly to its corresponding register
so now it looks like these instructions
have never executed or issued for that
matter and we can begin fetching from
the correct place updating the renaming
as a result of that and updating the
issue pointed as a result of that as you
can see with the raw based processor we
can do instructions out of order but we
still can figure out what the correct
order should have been if we did the
right thing at the point of the branch
so as you can see here we have executed
these instructions before we figured out
the branch but we are still able to undo
this damage overall the recovery with a
Rob based processor consists of making
the right entry point to their
corresponding registers who can erase
all of the renaming emptying out
whatever is in the Rob after we commit
the offending branch instruction
and of course getting rid of whatever is
left over in the reservation stations in
the area so basically free all the
reservation stations and stop the areas
from broadcasting results in the future
so if one of these instructions is still
in the alias or reservation stations
it's going to be just dropped